The big news organization rejects the ultimatum from Defense
Minister Pete Hexa regarding the Pentagon's coverage.
If given the option to sign a series of restrictions that limit
and are not clear or lose physical access to the building,
almost every major media rejects to sign tonight,
including CNN,
Reuters,
Associated Press,
New York Times,
Wall Street Journal,
Politico,
Newsmax,
and many others.
Even Hexa's former employee,
Fox News,
said they would not sign these new
regulations before tonight's deadline.
In fact,
only one media has received these conditions as far as we know.
One America News.
According to the new rules,
asking for information from the Pentagon officials will not be
considered an activity that is protected based on the first amendment.
Meanwhile,
journalists who have the information of national security
secret or non-secret documents that are controlled must discuss
the matter with the Pentagon's office before publication.
In statements from CNN, Fox News, ABC,
CBS,
and NBC,
all media said that these new regulations would limit
journalists' ability to continue to give information to the country
and the world about important national security issues.
This policy has never happened before and
threatens the protection of the core journalists.
However,
President and Hexat previously threatened him in the White House.
I think I'm a little disturbed by the presence of the army and even,
you know,
high-ranking generals walking with you in their sleeves.
If they sign a letter of trust,
they will not try to make the army violate
the law by giving them secret information.
So, this makes sense, Mr. President.
We try to ensure national security is
respected and we are proud of this policy.
My source tonight is Barbara Star,
who spent more than 20 years as a correspondent for
the Pentagon CNN and is a member of the First Pentagon
Association and one of the best reporters I know.
Barbara,
as someone who covers the Pentagon broadly and deeply
like you and is highly respected by those you cover,
what do you think the implications are
if the news organization signs this?
That makes them all very sick.
What Hexat said is that you cannot ask for information from a source,
whether it is a secret or not,
unless you have permission,
which means you cannot go around the Pentagon and do your job,
which is reporting, talking to people,
doing what thousands of reporters in this country do every day.
He looks to have deliberately kept emphasizing that
reporters are trying to get military secret information.
That's not my experience and I dare to say it's not the
experience of most of my colleagues in the Pentagon.
Secret information is behind the locked door in the Pentagon.
We have reporters who do not have access there and only
talk to someone who does not ask for secret information.
That's not how it works.
And as far as the information is connected
to the source before it is published,
you know,
it will go into the inside.
I will hand it over to the press or press,
but it enters the world of the first
amendment violation and it violates the
job oath.
All those people take,
you know,
taking oaths to defend the Constitution.
No,
and that's talking about going to the office before it's published.
That's what the media has done.
When you write a story or you will report something,
you clearly ask for comments.
But the way he wrote it and I read his promise
today is quite open for interpretation.
But another part of this is where
reporters can go and where they cannot,
which is quite limited in the Pentagon.
But I want you to hear what Minister Hex said
about how this new rule will affect the matter.
Maybe the policy should be like the White House or other
military installations where you have to use a plan that identifies
that you are a person or you cannot go anywhere you want.
In the past,
Mr. President,
Pers could go anywhere in the Pentagon.
The most secret area in the world.
Is that true?
No,
not at all.
And he knows that and he should say what is true to the president.
The first reporters used a plan that
identified themselves as you do in the White House,
the
Department of Foreign Affairs,
Capitol Hill for several decades.
So it's been taken care of,
go wherever they want,
not at all.
A few months ago,
the HGP more limited the place where
reporters could even enter the Pentagon.
But before that, no.
They went to a place they had to visit.
They went to Starbucks to drink coffee in the morning.
But they didn't go to the secret area and
they didn't chase people in the basement.
Allow me to explain that.
However,
over the years I have been covering the Pentagon.
We all often meet with the Defense Minister or
Chief of Staff of the Joint Staff in the basement
and they will come to the Pers area to talk.
You know, hey, what's going on?
What are you doing?
How are you?
Eh,
there's a lot of communication that goes on.
What will disappear from the HECSAT?
I think he doesn't even understand it.
He will lose the ability to communicate
with millions of Americans who read blogs,
read the Koran,
watch TV,
to get military news,
to find out what is going on,
to find out how their money is spent,
what the troops are doing,
how the military family is doing,
how the women and minority groups are doing in the military.
He will have real difficulty communicating.
And that's very different from President Trump,
as you know,
Kathleen.
Eh,
Mr. Trump likes to talk to the media every day while he's on duty.
The HECSAT has almost never talked to the media.
And I think behind the scenes,
the big question that is being talked about
more and more is what the HECSAT is afraid of.
If he's afraid of a leak,
chase them who, according to him, leaked it.
If he's afraid of not showing the President how tough he is,
maybe he needs to start by telling the truth about what actually
happened to the media and the Pentagon and continue from there.
I think he will face a lot of problems because the reporters
will continue to report whether they are in the building or not.
Very good, Barbara Star, one of the best.
Thank you for joining us tonight.
I'm so happy you're back on CNN. Thank you.